What is Kṛṣṇa telling Arjuna?
Mit mond Kṛṣṇa Arjunának?
Earth, water, fire, air, ether, mind, intelligence, ego …
Föld, víz, tűz, levegő, éter, elme, intelligencia, ego...
these are My energy.
ezek az én energiám.
They’re My separated diverse energies of a lower quality.
Ők az én gyengébb minőségű, független változatos energiáim.
[The Central Conception of the Infinite]
[A Végtelen központi koncepciója]
But Arjuna, there’s another energy higher than this:
De Arjuna, van egy másik energia, nagyobb, mint ez:
the jīva-śakti, and it’s driving the universe.
a jīva-śakti, és ez működteti az univerzumot.
It’s the power. They’re all over the place.
Ez a hatalom. Ők mindenütt ott vannak.
Once, Prabhupād was saying, “There are many meanings of Kṛṣṇa.
Egyszer Prabhupād azt mondta: "Kṛṣṇa-nak sok jelentése van.
One meaning of Kṛṣṇa is ‘wandering’.”
Kṛṣṇa egyik jelentése: "vándor"."
So, he said, “The jivas are Kṛṣṇa,
Szóval azt mondta: „A jivák Kṛṣṇa,
they’re wandering throughout the universe.”
ők vándorolnak szerte a világegyetemben."
So, Kṛṣṇa’s also saying, “They’re My aṁśa.”
Így Kṛṣṇa is mondja: „Ők az én aṁśam."
They’re like—what does it say in Daśa-Mūla, Bhakti Vinod?
Ők, olyanok mint a - mit is mond a Daśa-Mūlaban, Bhakti Vinod?
Bhedābhed, they’re the same and different.
Bhedābhed. Ők azonosak és különbözőek.
Same same, but different.
Azonos azonos, de különböző.
So, if we make the mistake of seeing things as separate from Kṛṣṇa,
Tehát, ha elkövetjük azt a hibát, hogy a dolgokat Kṛṣṇától különállónak tekintjük,
that is not good.
az nem jó.
That’s actually part of the cause of our predicament,
Ez valójában része annak, ami a mi kínos helyzetünket okozza:
not seeing things related to Kṛṣṇa —what to speak of avatar.
nem látni a dolgokat Kṛṣṇához kapcsolódottnak — amiről az avatár beszél.
If we can see how energy and mundane things …
Ha látjuk, hogy az energia és a múlandó dolgok...
we can trace their position back to the central conception of the Infinite.
visszavezethetjük a helyzetüket a Végtelen központi koncepciójába.